<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RNAseq on Chatomics</title>
    <link>/categories/rnaseq/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RNAseq on Chatomics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming &#39;Tommy&#39; Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/rnaseq/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to preprocess GEO bulk RNAseq data with salmon </title>
      <link>/post/how-to-preprocess-geo-bulk-rnaseq-data-with-salmon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-preprocess-geo-bulk-rnaseq-data-with-salmon/</guid>
      <description>Install fastq-dl To easily download fastq from GEO or ENA, use fastq-dl
Assume you already have conda installed, do the following:
conda config --add channels conda-forge conda config --add channels bioconda conda create -n fastq_download -c conda-forge -c bioconda fastq-dl conda activate fastq_download  Tip: use mamba if conda is too slow for you. They are all big snakes!!
We will use bulk RNAseq data from this GEO accession ID: https://www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to convert raw counts to TPM for TCGA data and make a heatmap across cancer types</title>
      <link>/post/how-to-convert-raw-counts-to-tpm-for-tcga-data-and-make-a-heatmap-across-cancer-types/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-convert-raw-counts-to-tpm-for-tcga-data-and-make-a-heatmap-across-cancer-types/</guid>
      <description>Sign up for my newsletter to not miss a post like this https://divingintogeneticsandgenomics.ck.page/newsletter
The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) project is probably one of the most well-known large-scale cancer sequencing project. It sequenced ~10,000 treatment-naive tumors across 33 cancer types. Different data including whole-exome, whole-genome, copy-number (SNP array), bulk RNAseq, protein expression (Reverse-Phase Protein Array), DNA methylation are available.
TCGA is a very successful large sequencing project. I highly recommend learning from the organization of it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>