<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bioconductor on DNA confesses Data speak</title>
    <link>/tags/bioconductor/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bioconductor on DNA confesses Data speak</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming &#39;Tommy&#39; Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/bioconductor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create pseudobulk from single-cell RNAseq data </title>
      <link>/post/how-to-create-pseudobulk-from-single-cell-rnaseq-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-create-pseudobulk-from-single-cell-rnaseq-data/</guid>
      <description>What is pseduobulk? Many of you have heard about bulk-RNAseq data. What is pseduobulk?
Single-cell RNAseq can profile the gene expression at single-cell resolution. For differential expression, psedobulk seems to perform really well(see paper muscat detects subpopulation-specific state transitions from multi-sample multi-condition single-cell transcriptomics data). To create a pseudobulk, one can artificially add up the counts for cells from the same cell type of the same sample.
In this blog post, I’ll guide you through the art of creating pseudobulk data from scRNA-seq experiments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to make a triangle correlation heatmap with p-values labeled </title>
      <link>/post/how-to-make-a-triangle-correlation-heatmap-with-p-values-labeled/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-make-a-triangle-correlation-heatmap-with-p-values-labeled/</guid>
      <description>In this blog post, I am going to show you how to make a correlation heatmap with p-values and significant values labeled in the heatmap body. Let’s use the PBMC single cell data as an example.
You may want to read my previous blog post How to do gene correlation for single-cell RNAseq data.
Load libraries library(dplyr) library(Seurat) library(patchwork) library(ggplot2) library(ComplexHeatmap) library(SeuratData) library(hdWGCNA) library(WGCNA) set.seed(1234)  prepare the data data(&amp;quot;pbmc3k&amp;quot;) pbmc3k #&amp;gt; An object of class Seurat #&amp;gt; 13714 features across 2700 samples within 1 assay #&amp;gt; Active assay: RNA (13714 features, 0 variable features) ## routine processing pbmc3k&amp;lt;- pbmc3k %&amp;gt;% NormalizeData(normalization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to do gene correlation for single-cell RNAseq data (part 2) using meta-cell </title>
      <link>/post/how-to-do-gene-correlation-for-single-cell-rnaseq-data-part-2-using-meta-cell/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-do-gene-correlation-for-single-cell-rnaseq-data-part-2-using-meta-cell/</guid>
      <description>In my last blog post, I showed that pearson gene correlation for single-cell data has flaws because of the sparsity of the count matrix.
One way to get around it is to use the so called meta-cell. One can use KNN to find the K nearest neighbors and collapse them into a meta-cell. You can implement it from scratch, but one should not re-invent the wheel. For example, you can use metacells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partial least square regression for marker gene identification in scRNAseq data</title>
      <link>/post/partial-least-square-regression-for-marker-gene-identification-in-scrnaseq-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/partial-least-square-regression-for-marker-gene-identification-in-scrnaseq-data/</guid>
      <description>This is an extension of my last blog post marker gene selection using logistic regression and regularization for scRNAseq.
Let’s use the same PBMC single-cell RNAseq data as an example.
Load libraries
library(Seurat) library(tidyverse) library(tidymodels) library(scCustomize) # for plotting library(patchwork) Preprocess the data
# Load the PBMC dataset pbmc.data &amp;lt;- Read10X(data.dir = &amp;quot;~/blog_data/filtered_gene_bc_matrices/hg19/&amp;quot;) # Initialize the Seurat object with the raw (non-normalized data). pbmc &amp;lt;- CreateSeuratObject(counts = pbmc.data, project = &amp;quot;pbmc3k&amp;quot;, min.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obtain metadata for public datasets in GEO</title>
      <link>/post/obtain-metadata-for-public-datasets-in-geo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/obtain-metadata-for-public-datasets-in-geo/</guid>
      <description>There are so many public datasets there waiting for us to mine! It is the blessing and cursing as a computational biologist!
Metadata, or the data describing (e.g., responder or non-responder for the treatment) the data are critical in interpreting the analysis. Without metadata, your data are useless.
People usually go to GEO or ENA to download public data. I asked this question on twitter, and I will show you how to get the metadata as suggested by all the awesome tweeps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Develop Bioconductor packages with docker container</title>
      <link>/post/develop-bioconductor-packages-with-docker-container/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/develop-bioconductor-packages-with-docker-container/</guid>
      <description>Readings links to read:
 https://www.bioconductor.org/developers/package-guidelines/#rcode
 https://github.com/Bioconductor/Contributions
 use container https://github.com/Bioconductor/bioconductor_full
  I am following the last link.
pull the container docker pull bioconductor/bioconductor_full:devel docker images REPOSITORY TAG IMAGE ID CREATED SIZE bioconductor/bioconductor_full devel ae3ec2be7376 3 hours ago 5.7GB seuratv3 latest 9b358ab1fd63 2 days ago 2.76GB  It is 5.7G in size.
start the Rstuido from the image. I have another Rstudio instance using port 8787, let me use a different one (e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>