<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on Chatomics</title>
    <link>/categories/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on Chatomics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming &#39;Tommy&#39; Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Spatial Transcriptomics A Dive into Visium Data Analysis in Python</title>
      <link>/post/python-visium/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/python-visium/</guid>
      <description>Why guest posting? I want to write more hands-on tutorials, but I realized:
 I am not an expert for every data type. I am too busy to write new ones.  So that&amp;rsquo;s why I started to experiment guest posting!
If you want to do a guest posting in my blog which gets 30k views per month, feel free to contact me on LinkedIn.
I love to collaborate and share knowledge!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to separate a comma delimited string into multiple lines in R and python </title>
      <link>/post/how-to-separate-a-comma-delimited-string-into-multiple-lines-in-r-and-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/how-to-separate-a-comma-delimited-string-into-multiple-lines-in-r-and-python/</guid>
      <description>To not miss a post like this, sign up for my newsletter to learn computational biology and bioinformatics.
The problem df&amp;lt;- data.frame(id = c(1,2,3), value = c(&amp;#39;x,y&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;z,w&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;a&amp;#39;)) df #&amp;gt; id value #&amp;gt; 1 1 x,y #&amp;gt; 2 2 z,w #&amp;gt; 3 3 a we want to put x,y in the first row into two rows:
1, x
1, y
and put z,w into two rows too.
 solution with R There is a neat function separate_rows that does exactly this in tidyr package:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My opinionated selection of books/urls for bioinformatics/data science curriculum</title>
      <link>/post/my-opinionated-selection-of-books-for-bioinformatics-data-science-curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/my-opinionated-selection-of-books-for-bioinformatics-data-science-curriculum/</guid>
      <description>There was a paper on this topic: A New Online Computational Biology Curriculum.
I am going to provide a biased list below (I have read most of the books if not all). I say it is biased because you will see many books of R are from Hadely Wickham. I now use tidyverse most of the time.
Unix I suggest people who want to learn bioinformatics starting to learn unix commands first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Split a 10xscATAC bam file by cluster</title>
      <link>/post/split-a-10xscatac-bam-file-by-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/split-a-10xscatac-bam-file-by-cluster/</guid>
      <description>I want to split the PBMC scATAC bam from 10x by cluster id. So, I can then make a bigwig for each cluster to visualize in IGV.
The first thing I did was googling to see if anyone has written such a tool (Do not reinvent the wheels!). People have done that because I saw figures from the scATAC papers. I just could not find it. Maybe I need to refine my googling skills.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>