<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bioinformatics on DNA confesses Data speak</title>
    <link>/tags/bioinformatics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bioinformatics on DNA confesses Data speak</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/bioinformatics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>marker gene selection using logistic regression and regularization for scRNAseq </title>
      <link>/post/marker-gene-selection-using-logistic-regression-and-regularization-for-scrnaseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/marker-gene-selection-using-logistic-regression-and-regularization-for-scrnaseq/</guid>
      <description>why this blog post? I saw a biorxiv paper titled A comparison of marker gene selection methods for single-cell RNA sequencing data
 Our results highlight the efficacy of simple methods, especially the Wilcoxon rank-sum test, Student’s t-test and logistic regression
 I am interested in using logistic regression to find marker genes and want to try fitting the model in the [tidymodel](https://www.tidymodels.org/) ecosystsem and using different regularization methods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CANCER IMMUNOLOGIC DATA COMMONS(CIDC)</title>
      <link>/project/cimac-cidc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/cimac-cidc/</guid>
      <description>The CIMAC-CIDC Network is an NCI Cancer Moonshot initiative that provides cutting-edge technology and expertise in genomic, proteomic, and functional molecular analysis to enhance clinical trials in cancer immune therapies.
The four Cancer Immune Monitoring and Analysis Centers (CIMACs) are at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Stanford University, MD Anderson, and Mount Sinai.
I am now leading the bioinformatics effort in the Cancer Immunologic Data Commons(CIDC) as part of the NCI Cancer Moonshot project on cancer immunotherapy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>