<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine learning on DNA confesses Data speak</title>
    <link>/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine learning on DNA confesses Data speak</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning with Keras using MNST dataset </title>
      <link>/post/deep-learning-with-keras-using-mnst-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/deep-learning-with-keras-using-mnst-dataset/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Are you a machine learning practitioner or data analyst looking to broaden your skill set? Look nowhere else! This blog post will offer an introduction to deep learning, which is currently the hottest topic in machine learning. Using the well-known MNST dataset) and the Keras package, we will investigate the potential of deep learning.
A high-level deep learning package called Keras, which is based on TensorFlow, enables quick and simple experimentation with deep neural networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Partial least square regression for marker gene identification in scRNAseq data</title>
      <link>/post/partial-least-square-regression-for-marker-gene-identification-in-scrnaseq-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/partial-least-square-regression-for-marker-gene-identification-in-scrnaseq-data/</guid>
      <description>This is an extension of my last blog post marker gene selection using logistic regression and regularization for scRNAseq.
Let’s use the same PBMC single-cell RNAseq data as an example.
Load libraries
library(Seurat) library(tidyverse) library(tidymodels) library(scCustomize) # for plotting library(patchwork) Preprocess the data
# Load the PBMC dataset pbmc.data &amp;lt;- Read10X(data.dir = &amp;quot;~/blog_data/filtered_gene_bc_matrices/hg19/&amp;quot;) # Initialize the Seurat object with the raw (non-normalized data). pbmc &amp;lt;- CreateSeuratObject(counts = pbmc.data, project = &amp;quot;pbmc3k&amp;quot;, min.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>marker gene selection using logistic regression and regularization for scRNAseq </title>
      <link>/post/marker-gene-selection-using-logistic-regression-and-regularization-for-scrnaseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/marker-gene-selection-using-logistic-regression-and-regularization-for-scrnaseq/</guid>
      <description>why this blog post? I saw a biorxiv paper titled A comparison of marker gene selection methods for single-cell RNA sequencing data
 Our results highlight the efficacy of simple methods, especially the Wilcoxon rank-sum test, Student’s t-test and logistic regression
 I am interested in using logistic regression to find marker genes and want to try fitting the model in the tidymodel ecosystem and using different regularization methods.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>