<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Singularity on Chatomics</title>
    <link>/tags/singularity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Singularity on Chatomics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming &#39;Tommy&#39; Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/singularity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>build your own singularity image</title>
      <link>/post/build-your-own-singularity-image/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/build-your-own-singularity-image/</guid>
      <description>I was using the tidyverse rocker image on HPC by singularity pull. see my previous post.
Everything was OK until I encountered problems installing jpeg and Cairo R packages. Later, I also had an error installing scRepertoire dependency gsl.
It turns out I have to install debian packages inside the container:
$ apt update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt install -y --no-install-recommends libjpeg62-turbo-dev zlib1g-dev libpng-dev \ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt install -y --no-install-recommends libx11-dev libcairo2-dev libxt-dev \ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt install -y libgsl-dev  However, singularity file system is read-only.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Rstudio server with singularity on HPC</title>
      <link>/post/run-rstudio-server-with-singularity-on-hpc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/run-rstudio-server-with-singularity-on-hpc/</guid>
      <description>Background Please read the following before go ahead:
 what is docker?
 what is Rocker?
 what is singularity?
  from Harvard Research computing website: Odyssey has singularity installed.
 Why Singularity? There are some important differences between Docker and Singularity:
  Docker and Singularity have their own container formats. Docker containers may be imported to run via Singularity. Docker containers need root privileges for full functionality which is not suitable for a shared HPC environment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>