<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tutorial on Chatomics</title>
    <link>/categories/tutorial/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tutorial on Chatomics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming &#39;Tommy&#39; Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/tutorial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible Computing in Bioinformatics: Lessons from My Latest Talk</title>
      <link>/post/repro-comp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/repro-comp/</guid>
      <description>Hey everyone, it’s Tommy here. If you’ve been following my blog or my Twitter/X (@tangming2005), you know I love diving into the practical side of bioinformatics and genomics.
Recently, I gave a talk titled “Good Enough Practices for Reproducible Computing” at Moderna, where I spent a good chunk of time chatting about reproducible computing.
Why? Because in our field, where data is exploding and analyses get complex, making sure your work can be repeated—by you or anyone else—is a game-changer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create a GenomicRanges object in Bioconductor using canonical transcripts</title>
      <link>/post/canonical-tx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/canonical-tx/</guid>
      <description>To not miss a post like this, sign up for my newsletter to learn computational biology and bioinformatics.
Introduction to Annotation Data Packages in Bioconductor Accurate gene and transcript annotation is the foundation of many bioinformatics workflows, including RNA-seq analysis, functional genomics, and variant annotation.
In the R/Bioconductor ecosystem, dedicated annotation data packages make it easy for researchers to access, query, and leverage gene models sourced from major biological databases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Cancer Drugs Really Work</title>
      <link>/post/cancer-drug/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cancer-drug/</guid>
      <description>To not miss a post like this, sign up for my newsletter to learn computational biology and bioinformatics.
Suna was 28. She had melanoma. Chemo left her wrecked—her hair gone, her strength gone, and her hope fading. Doctors gave her weeks.
Then they tried something different.
It didn’t poison the tumor. It didn’t cut or burn. It woke up her immune system.
Her own T-cells found the cancer. Attacked it. Killed it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to calculate partial correlation controlling cancer types</title>
      <link>/post/partial-cor/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/partial-cor/</guid>
      <description>To not miss a post like this, sign up for my newsletter to learn computational biology and bioinformatics.
What is partial correlation Partial correlation measures the relationship between two variables while controlling for the effect of one or more other variables.
Suppose you want to know how X and Y are related, independent of how both are influenced by Z. Partial correlation helps answer:
 If we remove the influence of Z, is there still a connection between X and Y?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>