<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks &amp; Workshops on DNA confesses Data speak</title>
    <link>/talk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talks &amp; Workshops on DNA confesses Data speak</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Ming Tang</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Learn Computational Biology the Right Way</title>
      <link>/talk/2023-bioinfocongress/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 11:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2023-bioinfocongress/</guid>
      <description>As the Bioinforange platform, we prepare and share Turkish and English review articles, news articles, videos, and scientific short notes on many biological science fields, especially bioinformatics. At the same time, we organize seminars, workshops, conferences, and congress events with the participation of valuable scientists. We have a website called www.bioinforange.com (Turkish content) and www.bioinfocodes.com (English content). We are also present on all social media platforms as @bioinforange and @bioinfocodes. Our platform is followed by scientists and our student friends who are studying in many scientific fields.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible genomic data science</title>
      <link>/talk/2022-iscb-reproducible/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2022-iscb-reproducible/</guid>
      <description>I gave a talk on reproducible genomic data science at the International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB) Student Council Symposium 2022 and had a panel discussion together with Yo Yehudi on open science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single-Cell Analysis 101: Current Approaches and Open Questions</title>
      <link>/talk/2022-single-cell-abrf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 12:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2022-single-cell-abrf/</guid>
      <description>I gave a talk on single-cell analysis 101 in the ABRF2022 conference. Thank you, Ben Johnson for the inivtation. I enjoyed it! The slides and video can be found in the links above!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual postdoc Alternative careers event King&#39;s College London</title>
      <link>/talk/2022-alternative-path/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 06:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2022-alternative-path/</guid>
      <description> I shared my career path at the annual postdoc Alternative careers event King&amp;rsquo;s College London. I am glad that I can give some tips to the postdocs and reminds them alternative careers exist besides academia. (Starting at 36 min at the youtube video I linked above).
Event My career path in one slide: </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Career mentoring for Department of Genomic Medicine, MD Anderson Cancer Center</title>
      <link>/talk/2022-career-mentoring-mda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 06:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2022-career-mentoring-mda/</guid>
      <description> I shared my career path at a Career mentoring session for Department of Genomic Medicine, MD Anderson Cancer Center. I had the pleasure to see many old colleagues and mentors Dr.Andrew Futreal and Dr.Jianjun (Jay) Zhang.
Event </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible research in genomic data science</title>
      <link>/talk/2021-reproducible-rsg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 06:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2021-reproducible-rsg/</guid>
      <description>I gave a keynote talk on reproducible research in genomic data science at the ISCB SC RSG Turkey Student Symposium 2021 https://symposium.rsgturkey.com/. I really enjoyed the speaking. Thank you for the inivtation! The slides and video can be found in the links above. Enjoy!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast analysis of scATAC-seq data using a predefined set of genomic regions</title>
      <link>/talk/2021-fast-scatacseq/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2021-fast-scatacseq/</guid>
      <description>I am invited by Henry Rong in Center for Functional Cancer Epigenomics (CFCE) at Dana-Farber to give a presentation on Fast analysis of scATAC-seq data using a predefined set of genomic regions. This project was a enjoyable collabration with Davide Cittaro at San Raffaele Scientific Institute in Italy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>STAT115 single cell ATACseq lecture</title>
      <link>/talk/2021-stat115-scrnaseq-lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2021-stat115-scrnaseq-lecture/</guid>
      <description>I gave a guest lecture on single cell ATACseq for STAT115 to the Harvard students. The videos can be found at https://liulab-dfci.github.io/bioinfo-combio/scatac.html. slides can be found in the PDF as well. Shirley has put all her course videos in the above bookdown. Great resource for Bioinformatics!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PACT meeting update: single-cell and bulk ATAC-seq analysis pipelines</title>
      <link>/talk/2020-maestro-pact-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 11:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2020-maestro-pact-talk/</guid>
      <description>In the joint Partnership for Access to Clinical Trials (PACT) and CIMAC-CIDC Network Fall meeting. I presented the update for our bulk ATAC-seq pipeline and the MAESTRO single-cell workflow. I led the discussion of the adoption of single-cell ATAC-seq in the CIMAC trails afterwards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MAESTRO: Model-based Analyses of Single-cell Transcriptome and Regulome</title>
      <link>/talk/2020-maestro-broad-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 14:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2020-maestro-broad-talk/</guid>
      <description>I gave a talk on our single-cell RNA-seq and single-cell ATAC-seq analysis tool MAESTRO in the Broad Institute CC&amp;amp;E Seminar Series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>reproducible computing for your own benifit</title>
      <link>/talk/2020-reproducible-computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2020-reproducible-computing/</guid>
      <description>We are hiring several new computational biologists in Shirley Liu Lab. All the new hires together with wet lab people are going through a 5-week long intensive bioinformatics training: STAT115.
I am TAing for 2 weeks and I gave a talk on reproducible computing. Please find the PDF here and share!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools and tricks for a data scientist</title>
      <link>/talk/2020-tools-tricks-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2020-tools-tricks-data-science/</guid>
      <description>In the lab meeting today, I introduced some of the linux tricks and apps I have been using for my daily work. I consider myself as a genomic data scientist. It is a bioinformatician&amp;rsquo;s rebranding according to Jason Williams.
I am sharing the PDF here, hope you find some of the tricks are useful too!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harvard FAS informatics nanocourse</title>
      <link>/talk/2019-harvard-fas-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2019-harvard-fas-workshop/</guid>
      <description>In this 2-week long Harvard FAS informatics nanocourse, I co-taught snakemake for one afternoon and lead-instructed scRNAseq analysis for a full day.
 The snakemake workshop material was adapted from Titus Brown and can be found at https://github.com/crazyhottommy/2019-snakemake-Harvard-Informatics-nanocourse
 The scRNAseq workshop material was developed using workflowr and can be found at https://crazyhottommy.github.io/scRNA-seq-workshop-Fall-2019/
 The rest of the nanocourse material can be found at https://github.com/harvardinformatics/micro-course
  I used the carpentries teaching style.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible research in bioinformatics</title>
      <link>/talk/2019-bunkerhill-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 14:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2019-bunkerhill-talk/</guid>
      <description>I was invited to give a talk on reproducible bioinformatics research to the students in the Bunker Hill Community College in Boston, MA. I was so glad to introduce bioinformatics to the students and share my own perspectives on reproducible research.
The movie Good Will Hunting was shot there :)
Embed your slides or video here using shortcodes. Further details can easily be added using Markdown and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From cell line to command line: my journey to bioinformatics</title>
      <link>/talk/2018-uf-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2018-uf-talk/</guid>
      <description>I was invited to give a talk to my PhD Genetics and Genomics program at the University of Florida. I talked about my personal experience on how I started doing bioinformatics and shared tips and resources to get the students started their own journey into bioinformatics.
I am so glad to be back home!
Embed your slides or video here using shortcodes. Further details can easily be added using Markdown and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 Next-Gen Sequence Analysis Workshop</title>
      <link>/talk/2018-dibsi-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2018-dibsi-course/</guid>
      <description>I taught the ChIP-seq lesson for 2018 ANGUS Next-Gen Sequence Analysis Workshop held in UC Davis from 7/1/2018 to 7/14/2018, and TAed for the rest of the sessions. You can find my class link here and all the rest materials here. This is the first formal teaching I have done after I became a certified instructor for Data Carpentry. The same teaching skills applied!
Some tips for teaching:
 Be slow in pace Pause and have students ask questions Draw on white borad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GS01 1143 Introduction to Bioinformatics course</title>
      <link>/talk/2017-gsbs-chipseq-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2017-gsbs-chipseq-class/</guid>
      <description>I taught the ChIP-seq bioinformatics lab for the GS01 1143 Introduction to Bioinformatics course to ~30 people with diverse background. Some of them did not have any experience with terminals. I walked through the materials slowly and it was well received!
I developed the course materials here.
I plan to develope it to a Data Carpentry type of course materials, more work to come!
Enjoyed the teaching a lot!
Teaching in action!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University of Miami 2-day Software Carpentry workshop</title>
      <link>/talk/2015-miami-carpentry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/2015-miami-carpentry/</guid>
      <description>I was excited to teach Shell and R to a group of 20 biologists from the University of Miami. This event was sponsored by Software carpentry https://software-carpentry.org/ and the University of Miami. see the course info here.
It was great teaching experience for me!
Teaching in action!
Response
Well received by the students! Embed your slides or video here using shortcodes. Further details can easily be added using Markdown and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>